Gustav Davidson Papers MS038
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Books and Ephemera, 1613 -- 1986; MS038.002; 15.6 Linear Feet
  - Ogburn, Dorothy and Charlton: The Renaissance Man of England, 1955; MS038.002.011.00030 (Box 11)
    Dedication: For Mr. and Mrs. Gustav Davidson with all good wishes and the hope that they will be friends for ever. Dorothy Ogburn Charlton Ogburn October 1958 [also notations/corrections written in on page 57]; Coward-McCann Publishing; Wear to DJ and cracking of textblock; Introduction card paperclipped to front flap of DJ; Paperclip removed and card placed in front cover
  - Parsons, Marble Holmes: On Sun-dial Road, 1944; MS038.002.011.00031 (Box 11)
    Dedication: For Mr. Vinal with fond(?) wishes for a happy Christmas and New Year Marble Holmes Parsons; Kilham Stationery and Printing Company; Sticker attached to front cover; 187 of 250 copies
  - Paterson, Robert Hunter: Lo, God is Here, 1959; MS038.002.011.00032 (Box 11)
    Signature: Robert Hunter Paterson; Unknown publisher; Good condition
  - Petrarca, Francesco and Joseph Auslander, trans.: The Sonnets of Petrarch, 1931; MS038.002.011.00033 (Box 11)
    Signature: Joseph Auslander; Longsman, Green Publishing; Discoloration to spine
  - Petrarca, Francesco and Helen Lee Peabody, trans.: Madrigals and Odes, 1940; MS038.002.011.00034 (Box 11)
    Dedication: To Outerbridge Horsey with the affectionate (?) regards of the author. H.L.P.; Loker Raley Publisher; Front cover pulling away from textblock
  - Phillips, Stephen: Marpessa, 1901; MS038.002.011.00035 (Box 11)
    Dedication: Joseph Auslander for Gustav; John Lane Publisher; Some buckling of cloth on front cover, information glued to inside front cover, text block pulling from front cover; Originally in bag with Sunrise Trumpets, Bittersweet Poems, A Ballade Upon a Wedding and Letters to Women
  - Poe, Edgar Allen: The Raven and Other Poems, 1845; MS038.002.011.00036 (Box 11)
    Wiley and Putnam Publishing; Cover separated from text block and severe foxing throughout; contains four letters: one from Harris Lightfoot Forbes to GD donating book; 1 from GD to Paul North Rice of the NYPL; 1 from Rice to GD; and a second from Forbes to GD; Correspondence indicates this is a 1st edition
  - Postgate, R.W.: Pervigilium veneris incerti auctoris carmen de vere The eve of Venus in Latin and in English, 1924; MS038.002.011.00037 (Box 11)
    Signature: R. W. Postgate; Houghton Mifflin Publishing; Wear to spine and front cover, wrapped in tissue; Limited to 260 of with 250 sold in US this is number 87
  - Rembrandt von H. Knadfub, 1924; MS038.002.012.00001 (Box 12)
    Glassine cover and cardboard slip cover that is completely broken at end
  - Renzulli, Michele: John Keats, L'uomo e il poeta, 1956; MS038.002.012.00002 (Box 12)
    Dedication: To Mr. Gustav Davidson, an American poet with the compliments of the author a Philodelplium (?), Rome, Via Moreceuisio (?) 13 February 1956; F. Giordano Publisher; Very poor; front and back cover missing and a few pages detached, text block is very discolored and brittle; In Italian
  - Rhys, Ernest, ed.: The Prelude to Poetry, The English Poets in Defence and Praise of Their Own Art, 1894; MS038.002.012.00003 (Box 12)
    Date is approximate; J.M. Dent Publisher; Text block limited in opening capacity, wear to hinges; Lyric Poets Series
  - Rilke, Rainer Maria and Jesse Lemont, trans.: Poems, 1943; MS038.002.012.00004 (Box 12)
    Dedication: For Gustav Davidson, With all good wishes and sincere regard Jessie Lemont 13 September 1944; Columbia University Press; Good condition; Newspaper clipping inside front cover and bibliographic card in textblock; 1st edition
  - Robinson, Edwin Arlington: Talifer, 1933; MS038.002.012.00005 (Box 12)
    Signature: E Arlington Robinson (on colophon); Macmillian Press; Good condition with yellow sticker on cover; Signed 134 of 273 limited edition
  - Rollins, Carl Purington: B.R. America's Typographic Playboy, 1927; MS038.002.012.00006 (Box 12)
    Dedication: With kindest wishes to my sincere friend Gustav Davidson from Richard W. Ellis October 7th 1927; Richard Ellis Publisher; Paper gone from spine, housed in two pieces of violet paper; 451 of 500 printer's copy
  - Rosen, Stanley: Death in Egypt, 1952; MS038.002.012.00007 (Box 12)
    Signature: Stanley Rosen; Golden Goose Press; Textblock appears to be taped to cover
  - Rubin, Lawrence A.: Mighty Mac, The Official Picture History of the Mackinac Bridge, 1958; MS038.002.012.00008 (Box 12)
    Wayne State University Press; Tears to DJ; Glued in plate: Compliments of D.B. Steinman
  - Russell, Sydney King: Now I've Seen Everything, 1968; MS038.002.012.00009 (Box 12)
    Dedication: Happy Days to Gustav -- Sydney; House of Falmouth Press; Wear to DJ
  - Salkeld, John: A Treatis of Angels, 1613; MS038.002.012.00010 (Box 12)
    T.S. Publisher; Possibly rebound; Major discoloration to pages
  - Saltus, Edgar: Poppies and Mandragora, 1926; MS038.002.012.00011 (Box 12)
    Harold Vinal Publisher; Extensive wearing on cover edges; round yellow sticker on cover; separation in text block; Note inside "funded from 300 copies Georgian Paper 3/34; number 11 written on colophon
  - Sampley, Arthur M.: Selected Poems 1937-1971, MS038.002.012.00012 (Box 12)
    Dedication:For Mrs. Gustav Davidson with best wishes, Arthur M. Sampley; North Texas State University Press; Wear to DJ edges; 1st edition
  - Samuel H. Kress Foundation: The gospels of Saint Matthew, Saint Mark, Saint Luke and Saint John, together with the Acts of the Apostles, 1959; MS038.002.012.00013 (Box 12)
    Dedication: For Molly & Gustav With the affection & friendship of the Typographer and Printer Richard Ellis 1960; Samuel H. Kress Foundation Publisher; Paper DJ with gold monogram "M & G Davidson" and board slipcase which is detaching, dirty and fading; Compiled by Richard Ellis
  - Sandburg, Carl: A Lincoln Preface, 1953; MS038.002.012.00014 (Box 12)
    Harcourt, Brace, and Company Publishers; Paper from spine completely broken off; Originally in bag with sticker "limited to 52" and with To a Foil'd European Revolutionnaire
  - Schuh, Friedrich: Die Gotter der Griechen, 1959; MS038.002.012.00015 (Box 12)
    Dedication: In remembrance of our Greek tour 1957 where I received so much hospitality from you, Mrs. Davison, and all your compatriots Muischen, 27.12.59 Friedrich Schuh; Discoloration to cover and tears/folds to textblock in upper right corner; Also contains letter in German from Schuh in inside cover; post-it note from indeterminate date and author: 1st edition Ed Nast Millay
  - Sharp, William (Fiona Macleod): From the Hills of Dream, 1904; MS038.002.012.00016 (Box 12)
    Signature: Gustav Davidson 1924; Thomas B. Mosher Publisher; Date given as Mdcccciv; Very poor condition, signatures are almost completely separated, ribbon bookmark; This second edition on Van Gelder paper consists of 925 copies
  - Shaw, Elizabeth: Painted Maps, 1931; MS038.002.012.00017 (Box 12)
    Dedication: A rivedarci, Gustav dear. This with my love, as always. Elizabeth June 30, 1934; Dial Press; Good condition; Letter from Shaw inside front cover
  - Shelley, Percy Bysshe and Henry John Newbold: Poems of Shelley, MS038.002.012.00018 (Box 12)
    Thomas Nelson Publisher; Poor condition, front cover detached, leather flaking apart, textblock in good condition. No Date Available
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis: An Isaac Bashevis Singer Reader, 1971; MS038.002.013.00001 (Box 13)
    Dedication: Greetings I.B. Singer; Farrar, Straus and Giroux; Tears to paper cover; Originally in bag with Short Friday
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis: Enemies, A Love Story, 1972; MS038.002.013.00002 (Box 13)
    Farrar, Straus and Giroux Publishing; Very good condition; Originally in bag with Old Love, Satan in Goray and Prism 1, clipping and program (moved to envelope)
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis: Old Love, 1979; MS038.002.013.00003 (Box 13)
    Farrar, Straus and Giroux Publishing; Very good condition, DJ in mylar; Origianlly in bag with Enemies a Love Story, Satan in Goray and Prism 1, clipping and program (moved to envelope)
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis: Prism Magazine 1 featuring "The Last Demon", 1962; MS038.002.013.00004 (Box 13)
    Originally in bag with Enemies a Love Story, Satan in Goray and Old Love, clipping and program (moved to envelope)
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis: Satan in Goray, 1955; MS038.002.013.00005 (Box 13)
    Signature: Gustav Davidson; Noonday Press; Wear to DJ; Originally in bag with Old Love, Enemies a Love Story and Prism 1, clipping and program (moved to envelope)
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis: Short Friday, 1964; MS038.002.013.00006 (Box 13)
    Dedication: Greetings I.B. Singer; Farrar, Straus and Giroux Publishing; Indent from paperclip on backcover, DJ is dirty; Bibliographic card; Originally in bag with Isaac Bashevis Singer Reader
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis [Ephemera], 1983; MS038.002.013.00007 (Box 13)
    Program and clipping regarding Singer poetry reading, May 23, 1983; Originally in bag with Old Love, Enemies a Love Story, Satan in Goray and Prism 1
  - Smith, T.R. ed.: Poetica Erotica, A Collection of Rare and Curious Amatory Verse, 1931; MS038.002.013.00008 (Box 13)
    Horace Liveright Inc. Publishing; Good condition, yellow sticker on cover, deckles; 1303 of 3125 copies
  - Smith, William: A Smaller Classical Dictionary of Biography, Mythology, and Geography, 1886; MS038.002.013.00009 (Box 13)
    Harper and Brothers Publishing; Cloth on spine developing holes, text block breaking; Note in textblock for Zeus picture; Envelope used to made DJ
  - Smythe, Daniel: Brief Inheritance, 1952; MS038.002.013.00010 (Box 13)
    Signature: Daniel Smythe; Praire Press; Discoloration and torn edges of cover
  - Smythe, Daniel: Stange Elements, Selected Poems, 1966; MS038.002.013.00011 (Box 13)
    Dedication: For Gustav Davidson With every best wish and with admiration Cordially, Daniel Smythe; Golden Quill Press; Pages 25-26 missing; Bibliographic card in textblock
  - Speyer, Leonora: American Poets, An Anthology of Contemporary Verse, 1923; MS038.002.013.00012 (Box 13)
    Dedication: For Gustav with affection -- Leonora 1949; Spamer, Leipzig Publisher; Wear to edge of cover
  - Speyer, Leonora: Naked Heel, 1931; MS038.002.013.00013 (Box 13)
    Dedication: For Gustav with affection Leonora 1951; Knopf Publishing; Minor wear to DJ, last page is not opened; Originally in bag with A Garland of Elizabethan Sonnets, Ancient Pagan Symbols and Slow Wall
  - Speyer, Leonora: Slow Wall, 1939; MS038.002.013.00014 (Box 13)
    Dedication: For Gustav Davidson -- fellow poet and friend -- Leonora Speyer June1945; Knopf Publishing; Red sticker stuck to front cover; Originally in bag with A Garland of Elizabethan Sonnets, Ancient Pagan Symbols and Naked Heel
  - Speyer, Leonora: Slow Wall together with Nor Without Music, 1946; MS038.002.013.00015 (Box 13)
    Dedication: To Gustav and Mollie two dear friends from Leonora April 1946; Knopf Publishing; Acid migration inside front cover
  - Steffen, Albert and Daisy Alden trans.: The Collected Poems of Albert Steffen, 1968; MS038.002.014.00001 (Box 14)
    Dedication: For Gustav and Mollie - Licht, Liebe, Leben - Daisy Aldan 1970; Folder Editions; Very good condition
  - Steinhauer, Lillian: Poems, 1961; MS038.002.014.00002 (Box 14)
    Dedication: To Mrs. Gustave Davidson The charming poet who fostered poetic genius in Gustave Davidson Sincerely Lillian Steinhauer 1973; Greenwich Book Publishers; Very good condition; 1st edition
  - Steinman, David B.: Famous Bridges of the World, 1953; MS038.002.014.00003 (Box 14)
    Dedication: To Gustav Davidson Poet and Artist In sincere admiration DB Steinman 1955; Random House Publishing; Discoloration and acid transfer on inside of DJ; Correspondence, poem and program moved from front cover to envelope and folder
    Bridges (built works)
  - Steinman, David B.: Famous Bridges of the World [Ephemera], 1953; MS038.002.014.00004 (Box 14)
    Correspondence, poem and program moved from front cover of book
  - Steuben Glass: Engraved Crystal, 1961; MS038.002.014.00005 (Box 14)
    Published by Steuben Glass; Boards are warped; Clippings removed to envelope; See also subject files and oversized box for related materials
  - Steuben Glass: Engraved Crystal [Ephemera], 1961; MS038.002.014.00006 (Box 14)
  - Stickney, Helen Frith: Prelude to Winter, 1934; MS038.002.014.00007 (Box 14)
    Dedication: To Marguirite Adams. With affectionate regard -- Helen Frith Stickney; Banner Press; Good condition; Letter to Mrs. Adams from Mary A. Kukuh inside front cover
  - Stork, Charles Wharton ed.: Second Contemporary Verse Anthology, 1920-1923, MS038.002.014.00008 (Box 14)
    Dedication: Many happy returns of the day to Marguerite, with love from Edmund, September 20th/23; Dutton Press; Wear and discoloration to cover, spine label flaking, last page is not opened; "This first edition is limited to 1500 copies"
  - Suckling, John: A Ballade upon a Wedding, 1901; MS038.002.014.00009 (Box 14)
    Dedication: Gustav Davidson (from Joseph Auslander); John Lane Publisher; Text block breaking out of cover; front leaf with inscription completely detached; Originally in bag with Sunrise Trumpets, Bittersweet poems, Marpessa, and Letters to Women
  - Summers, Montague trans.: Malleus Maleficarium, 1928; MS038.002.014.00010 (Box 14)
    Bookplate for Helen Hunt Hamilton; John Rodker Publisher; Faded paper (not original) DJ; hinges loosening; flaking pages; Loose descriptive sheet (possiblly for a discarded slipcase or DJ)
  - Swallow, Alan: The War Poems of Alan Swallow, 1948; MS038.002.014.00011 (Box 14)
    Fine Editions Press; Textblock was stapled to cover and has pulled out completely, paper cover has come completely unglued from boards; Postcard signed by Swallow inside front cover
  - Swinburne, Algernon Charles: Songs Before Sunrise, 1922; MS038.002.014.00012 (Box 14)
    William Heineman Publisher; Minor wear to corners and spine
  - Tennyson, Alfred Lord: The Poetical Works of Alfred Tennyson, 1868; MS038.002.014.00013 (Box 14)
    Ticknor and Fields Publisher; Possibly rebound; Front pages detaching; Volume 1 of 2
  - Tennyson, Alfred Lord: In Memoriam, 1901; MS038.002.014.00014 (Box 14)
    Bookplate for Gustav Davidson; Macmillian Press; Front cover completely detached and text block separating; Fourth Macmillian printing according to verso
  - Thompson, Francis: The Hound of Heaven, 1907; MS038.002.014.00015 (Box 14)
    Date is approximate; Burns, Oates and Washbourne Ltd. Publishing; Very fragile with detached cover; In frail brown envelope wrapper with title and word "rare" on it
  - Tolstoy, Lev N. and Leo Weiner, trans.: War and Peace Volumes III and IV, 1904; MS038.002.014.00016 (Box 14)
    Signature: Gustav Davidson 1923; Colonial Press Company; Back cover and part of text block detached, spine broken off, wear to front cover; Scraps of paper marking pages; Illustrated Library Edition
  - Transition Journal, 1927; MS038.002.014.00017 (Box 14)
    Very poor condition; Includes "An Elucidation" by Gertrude Stein and "Opening Pages of a Work in Progress" by James Joyce (Finnagin's Wake)
  - Transition Journal [Ephemera], 1927; MS038.002.014.00018 (Box 14)
    Envelope journal was housed in
  - Tuttle, Charles E.: Japan, Theme and Variations, 1959; MS038.002.014.00019 (Box 14)
    Charles E. Tuttle Company Publishing; Red dot sticker on front cover, Severe discoloration to spine
  - Vanbrugh, John: Plays Volume 1 and 2, 1759; MS038.002.015.00001 (Box 15)
    First volume is 370 pages, second volume is 342 pages; Published in London; Headband unraveling, boards detatching, extensive discoloration of edges inside cover and first leaves; Auction slip
  - Viereck, George Sylvester: My Flesh and Blood, A Lyric Autobiography, with Indiscreet Annotations, 1931; MS038.002.015.00002 (Box 15)
    Dedication: Poeta Americanus sum et supra factum and Tubal was the first poet in my universe George Sylvester Viereck Gustav Davidson 1957; H. Liveright Publisher; Discoloration to cover, especially spine, Some pages detaching; Originally in bag with My First Two Thousand Years and Roosevelt
  - Viereck, George Sylvester: Roosevelt, A Study in Ambivalence, 1920; MS038.002.015.00003 (Box 15)
    Jackson Press; Original DJ very deteriorated, covered with a homemade slipcover, correspondence and photo removed to envelope; Originally in bag with My Flesh and Blood and My First Two Thousand Years; 2nd edition 6th printing
  - Viereck, George Sylvester: Roosevelt, A Study in Ambivalence [Ephemera], 1920; MS038.002.015.00004 (Box 15)
    Christmas card and photo of author removed from book
  - Viereck, George Sylvester and Paul Eldridge: My First Two Thousand Years: the Autobiography of the Wandering Jew, 1942; MS038.002.015.00005 (Box 15)
    Dedication: To Gustav Davidson, Poet -- Very Cordially Paul Eldridge May 23, 1945 Even more cordially George Sylvester Viereck May 30/ 1957; Gold Label Press; DJ torn and fragile, chapbook "The Bankrupt" in textblock, correspondence from inside front cover moved to envelope; Origianlly in bag with My Flesh and Blood and Roosevelt
  - Viereck, George Sylvester and Paul Eldridge: My First Two Thousand Years: the Autobiography of the Wandering Jew [Ephemera], 1942; MS038.002.015.00006 (Box 15)
    5 letters and 2 articles on expulsion of Viereck from Poetry Society of America
  - Vinal, Harold: Attic for the Nightingale, A Sheaf of Informal Essays, 1934; MS038.002.015.00007 (Box 15)
    Dedication: To Molly, remembering [illegible] Harold Vinal July 1942; Stephen Daye Publisher; Wear at spine, deckles
  - Vidal, Harold ed.: The Continential Anthologies First Series, 1929; MS038.002.015.00008 (Box 15)
    "Avison" written on inside first page; Roger Lacouriere Publisher; Glassine cover broken at spine, additional wear through spine paper to reveal signatures; Scrap of paper with # sign on it; #277 of 550 printed on colophon
  - Warren, Robert Penn: Eleven Poems on the Same Theme, 1942; MS038.002.015.00009 (Box 15)
    New Directions Publishing; DJ removed due to tearing; Materials housed in envelope
  - Webb, Mary: Poems and the Spring of Joy, 1948; MS038.002.015.00010 (Box 15)
    Signature: Virginia Kent Cummins; Jonathan Cape, Limited Publishing; Worn DJ and priceclipped
  - Wheelock, John Hall: This Blessed Earth, New and Selected Poems, 1927-1977, 1978; MS038.002.015.00011 (Box 15)
    Scribner Publishing; Like new; Correspondence removed to envelope; Originally in bag alone
  - Wheelock, John Hall: This Blessed Earth, New and Selected Poems, 1927-1977 [Ephemera], 1978; MS038.002.015.00012 (Box 15)
  - Whitman, Walt: To a Foil'd European Revolutionnaire, 1955; MS038.002.015.00013 (Box 15)
    Oriole Press; Very good condition; Limited to 52 copies for private distribution; Originally in bag with sticker "limited to 52" and with A Lincoln Preface
  - Williams, Oscar: A Little Treasury of Modern Poetry, 1946; MS038.002.015.00014 (Box 15)
    Dedication: For Gustav and Mollie With all affectionate wishes Jessie S [illegible] Yuletide 1946; Charles Scribner Publishing; Ribbon bookmark faded; Very brittle clippings from inside back cover rehoused in envelope, clipping in textblock left in place
  - Williams, Oscar: A Little Treasury of Modern Poetry [Ephemera], 1946; MS038.002.015.00015 (Box 15)
    Fragile and brittle clippings removed from book
  - Williamson, W. M.: The Eternal Sea, An Anthology of Sea Poetry, 1946; MS038.002.015.00016 (Box 15)
    Dedication: Happy Birthday to Walt from [Ueorlies] Oct 21st 1946; Coward-McCann; DJ missing, sticker stuck to front cover
  - Williamson, W.M.: The Eternal Sea, An Anthology of Sea Poetry, 1946; MS038.002.015.00017 (Box 15)
    Dedication: To Gustav - who also loves the poetry of the great world of waters - Sincerely Bill Williamson 12/5/54; Coward-McCann Publisher; DJ is worn
  - Wurdemann, Audrey: The Bright Ambush, Poems, 1934; MS038.002.015.00018 (Box 15)
    Dedication: for Irving Marlin, with my best wishes and appreciation Richard Ellis 8th February 1934; John Day Publication; Some wear and discoloration to cover
  - Wurdemann, Audrey: The Seven Sins, 1935; MS038.002.015.00019 (Box 15)
    Dedication: For Gustav "The disciplined dark hand can prove with what far dreams the mind in full" Audrey Wurdemann Nov. 4, 1935; Harper Press; DJ is almost completely broken at spine; Clippings and postcard inserted through text
  - Yeats, William Butler: The Collected Poems of W. B. Yeats, 1951; MS038.002.015.00020 (Box 15)
    Signature: Oliver St. J. Gogarty; notations in table of contents; Macmillian Press; Good condition; Note taped to inside of front cover: unpublished poem of WB Yeats written out from memory by Oliver St. John Gogarty (see fly leaf, in back) pencil notation (page x) by Gogarty -- poem Crazy Jane and the King is written on back fly leaf; Photo of drawing of Yeats which was rehoused in an small envelope
  - Yeats, William Butler: The Collected Poems of W. B. Yeats, 1951; MS038.002.015.00021 (Box 15)
    Photo of drawing of Yeats removed from book
  - Young, Barbara: A Study of Kahlil Gibran This Man from Lebanon, 1931; MS038.002.015.00022 (Box 15)
    Signature: Barbara Young; Syrian American Press; Glassine cover cracked and detaching, major wear to paper cover; With note card with bibliographic info and note from title page; First edition; 209 of 250 copies
  - Yuzon, Amado M.: The Citizen's Poems, The Nation's Number 1 Citizen, 1956; MS038.002.015.00023 (Box 15)
    Letter from Yuzon to Davidson written on first leaf; Commercial Press; Poems written by Yuzon to Davidson in envelope; number 112 of 5000; 1st edition
  - Alighieri, Dante and Henry Francis Cary trans.: The Inferno from La Divina Commedia of Dante Alighieri, 1931; MS038.002.016.00001 (Box 16)
    Dedication: To Gustav The man who puts into words the thoughts we have. Sincerely, Walter P. Chrysler; Cheshire House Publishing; William Blake Plates; Very poor condition, leather is flaking; Box also contains one letter and one card with a photograph; Limited edition of 1200 copies